Raghav Gnanasambandam

Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, VA

∠ raghavg**@**vt.edu

★ raghavg97.github.io

in raghav-g

EDUCATION

Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, VA

2019 - Present

Ph.D. in Industrial and Systems Engineering

- Advisor: Prof. Zhenyu (James) Kong
- Dissertation: Physics-informed Machine Learning for Digital Twin in Metal Additive Manufacturing
- Graduate Certificate: Future Professoriate Certificate
- GPA: 3.9/4

Indian Institute of Technology (IIT) Madras, Chennai, India

2014 - 2019

Dual Degree (B.Tech & M.Tech) in Mechanical Engineering

- Specialization: Intelligent Manufacturing
- Thesis: Machine Vision-Based Surface Characterization & Roughness Prediction of Machined Surfaces
- Minor: Materials Science
- GPA: 8.2/10

RESEARCH STATEMENT

My research is to enable **Digital Twins** for **Advanced Manufacturing** by process modeling. I developed a novel activation function for **Physics-Informed Neural Networks** (PINNs) to solve multi-scale **Partial Differential Equation** (PDE) systems. I am working on first-of-its-kind simulator for **Laser Powder Bed Fusion** (L-PBF) with PINNs. I proposed a novel **Bayesian Optimization** algorithm for optimizing the process parameters.

AWARDS & ACHIEVEMENTS

- Outstanding PhD Student (2023), ISE at Virginia Tech
 - For research work, honors, and service
 - Awarded cash prize of \$600
- Winner, IISE QCRE ProcessMiner Industrial Data Challenge 2023
 - Proposed Seq-2-Seq LSTM model for Fungal Spores prediction in paper industry
 - Achieved highest prediction accuracy among 8 participants
 - Awarded cash prize of \$1,000
- Travel Awards (2022-2023), ISE at Virginia Tech
 - Conference Travel Awards worth \$2,000
- Winner, IISE QCRE ProcessMiner Industrial Data Challenge 2022
 - Developed a novel activation function for deep learning
 - Awarded cash prize of \$2,000
- Winner, INFORMS DMDA Workshop Poster Competition 2022
 - Presented a <u>video</u> of my research poster
 - Awarded cash prize of \$500
- Finalist, INFORMS QSR Data Challenge 2022
 - Developed a novel method for anomaly detection and root-cause analysis for Ford Motor Company
 - $One\ of\ the\ four\ finalists$
- ISE Graduate Fellowship (2019-2020), Virginia Tech
 - Awarded \$9,765 over 9 months
- Undergraduate Scholarship (2014-2019), NLC India Ltd.

JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

Published/Accepted

- 1. R. Gnanasambandam, B. Shen, J. Chung, X. Yue, and Z.J. Kong. "Self-scalable Tanh (Stan): Multiscale Solutions for Physics-Informed Neural Networks". *IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence* (Impact Factor 23.6). [Paper] [Codes]
 - Winner, IISE QCRE ProcessMiner Data Challenge Competition 2022
 - Winner, INFORMS DMDA Workshop Poster Competition 2022
- 2. B. Shen, **R. Gnanasambandam**, R. Wang, and Z.J. Kong. "Multi-task Gaussian Process Upper Confidence Bound for Hyperparameter Tuning and its Application for Simulation Studies of Additive Manufacturing." *IISE Transactions* 55.5 (2023): 496-508. [Paper]
 - Developed and implemented the Single-task version of algorithm
- 3. V. Akhil, R. Gnanasambandam, N. Arunachalam, and D.S. Srinivas. "Image Data-Based Surface Texture Characterization and Prediction Using Machine Learning Approaches for Additive Manufacturing." J. Comput. Inf. Sci. Eng. 20.2 (2020): JCISE-19-1222. [Paper]
 - Handled the entire image-feature extraction and machine learning [Codes]
- 4. V. Akhil, N. Arunachalam, **R. Gnanasambandam**, and D.S. Srinivas. "Surface Texture Characterization of Selective Laser Melted Ti-6Al-4V Components using Fractal Dimension and Lacunarity Analysis." *Proceedings of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers, Part B: Journal of Engineering Manufacture* (2020). [Paper]
 - Built the characterization models [Codes]

Under Review/Revision

- R. Gnanasambandam, B. Shen, A.C.C. Law, C. Dou, and Z.J. Kong. "Deep Gaussian Process for Enhanced Bayesian Optimization and its Application in Additive Manufacturing". Minor Revision (2nd round). IISE Transactions. [Preprint]
- 6. R. Wang, R. Wang, C. Dou, S. Yang, **R. Gnanasambandam**, A. Wang, and Z.J. Kong. "Novel Fiber Optic Sensing with Extra High Spatial Resolution Enabled by Machine Learning and its Application for Sub-surface Thermal Measurement in Additive Manufacturing Processes". Manuscript Submitted (August 2023). *Nature Communications*.
 - Developed the machine learning framework

In Preparation

- 7. R. Gnanasambandam, C. Dou, and Z.J. Kong. "Physics-informed Machine Learning based Fast Prediction for Dynamic Thermal Distribution of Additive Manufacturing". To be submitted to IISE Transactions by November 2023.
- 8. **R. Gnanasambandam**, J. Chung, Y. Zhang, C. Li, M. Marena, N.R. Jordan, B. Shen, and Z.J. Kong. "A Holistic Data Analytics Framework for Laser Powder Bed Fusion". *To be submitted to Journal of Intelligent Manufacturing Systems by December 2023*.
- 9. J. Chung, **R. Gnanasambandam**, Y. Zhang, Z.J. Kong, and B. Shen. "Automatic Thresholding by Reconstruction Error in Unsupervised Anomaly Detection in Automotive Industry". *To be submitted to Journal of Intelligent Manufacturing Systems by December 2023*.
 - Equal contribution with first author
 - Finalist, INFORMS QSR Data Challenge 2022

PROJECTS

• Office of Naval Research Multidisciplinary University Research Initiatives (MURI)

2019-2024

- <u>Topic</u>: Rationalization of Interphase Instabilities During Thermo-Mechanical <u>Gyrations Typical to Metal Additive Manufacturing (AM)</u>
- Collaboration with Materials Scientists
- Contributed in Physics-informed Machine Learning for Laser Powder Bed Fusion

• IIT Madras & Prisms India Pvt. Ltd.

2017-2018

- Topic: Automation of Straightness Measurement in Autocollimator with a Vision System
- Built the software interface to process real time video data from Autocollimator

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

• Industrial Cost Control (ISE 3004), GTA, Virginia Tech

Spring 2021

- One of the two GTAs for a class of 120 students
- Facilities and Logistics (ISE 3214), GTA, Virginia Tech

Fall 2019 & 2020

- One of the four GTAs for a class of 200 students
- Manufacturing Processes Lab (ISE 2214), GTA, Virginia Tech

Spring 2020

- Sole lab instructor for 8-10 students per experiment (with 250 enrolled students)
- Handled the online transition due to COVID-19
- Measurement, Instrumentation, and Control (ME 2400), GTA, IIT Madras

Spring 2019

- Instructor for tutorial classes (1 class per week) with 75 students
- Machine Drawing Practice (Lab Instructor) (ME 2050), GTA, IIT Madras

Fall 2018

- Assisted students on 3D CAD modeling
- One of the two TAs for a class of 200 students
- Guest Lecturer, AI in Manufacturing (ME 7150), IIT Madras

Spring 2019

- Invited for presenting my course project from Spring 2018

WORK EXPERIENCE

• RF Wave Technologies Pvt. Ltd., Intern, Chennai, India

Summer 2017

- Worked on developing sensor and data logging systems for a farm-bot
- Awarded performance-based bonus for the entire duration of internship

RESEARCH TALKS

• Thermal Modeling with Physics-Informed Machine Learning

- INFORMS Annual Meeting 2022, Indianapolis, IN (Invited)
- ONR MURI Fifth Year Review (2023), San Diego, CA
- IISE Annual Conference 2023, New Orleans, LA (Invited)

• Self-scalable Tanh (Stan) for Multi-scale Solutions in Physics-Informed Neural Networks

- IISE QCRE ProcessMiner Data Challenge 2022, Seattle, WA (Winner)
- IISE Annual Conference 2022, Seattle, WA (Invited)
- INFORMS DMDA Workshop 2022, Indianapolis, IN

• A Holistic Data Analytics Framework for Laser Powder Bed Fusion

- ICQSR Data Challenge 2023, Raleigh, NC (Sole Participant)
- Sequence-to-Sequence LSTM for Fungal Spores Concentration Prediction
 - IISE QCRE ProcessMiner Data Challenge 2023, New Orleans, LA (Winner)

• Bayesian Optimization with Stochastic Imputation of Deep Gaussian Process

- INFORMS Annual Meeting 2021, Anaheim, CA (Invited)
- INFORMS Annual Meeting 2022, Indianapolis, IN (Invited)
- IISE Annual Conference 2023, New Orleans, LA

RESEARCH POSTERS

- Physics-informed NN Modeling and Closed-loop Control for Metal Additive Manufacturing
 - MELD (Friction Stir AM) User Meeting, Blacksburg, VA

August 2023

- Bayesian Optimization with Stochastic Imputation of Deep Gaussian Process
 - IISE Annual Conference, New Orleans, LA

May 2023

- Self-Scalable Tanh for Physics-Informed Neural Networks
 - IISE Annual Conference, Seattle, WA

May 2022

- INFORMS DMDA Workshop, Indianapolis, IN (Winner)

October 2022

MENTORING EXPERIENCE

- Mentor, Project EduAccess 2022-2023
 - Assisted 2 students from marginalized communities (in India) for graduate admissions in the US
- Project Leader at Intl. Networked Team for Engg. Des. & Innov. (MANE 4173, UTRGV) 2022
 - Lead a project on Emergency Deployable Structures
 - Interdisciplinary team with 3 undergraduates from UTRGV and a Master's student from Mexico

SERVICE

- Session Chair, Data-driven Approaches for CPS, INFORMS Annual Meeting 2023
- VP Operations, INFORMS Student Chapter, Virginia Tech 2023-2024
 - Winners, Student Chapter Magna Cum Laude
- Panelist, Graduate School Orientation Spring 2023, Virginia Tech
- Graduate Student Ambassador (2022-2023), Virginia Tech
- Research Poster Judge, ISE Senior Symposium 2022 & 2023, Virginia Tech
- Student Volunteer, HBCU/MSI Research Summit 2022, Virginia Tech
- Student Volunteer, ISE Senior Symposium 2021, Virginia Tech
- Secretary, Society of Manufacturing Engineers (SME) 2020-2021, Virginia Tech
- Peer Review
 - IEEE Transactions on Automation Science and Engineering (IEEE-TASE)
 - Journal of Intelligent Manufacturing (JIMS)
 - IISE Annual Conference (Manufacturing and Design Track)
 - Graduate Research Development Program (GRDP) at Virginia Tech

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

- Graduate Academy for Teaching Excellence at Virginia Tech (VT GrATE)
- Institute of Industrial and Systems Engineers (IISE)
- Institute for Operations Research and the Management Sciences (INFORMS)